{"tossups": [{"question": "This battle featured fierce fighting over the village of Ponyri, which gave one side the opportunity to launch Operation Kutuzov. Walther Model and Erich von Manstein aimed to pincer the namesake salient during this battle. Codenamed Citadel, this battle was delayed so that one side could wait for more Panthers. Tigers and T-34s clashed at Prokhorovka in, for ten points, what 1943 battle on the Eastern Front, the largest tank battle in history?", "answer": "Battle of<b> Kursk</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "While surveying the grounds for this project, its architect crushed his foot when it was trapped by a passing ferry, resulting in a tetanus infection that killed him. A physician involved in the creation of this project named Andrew Smith coined the name of a sickness that afflicted many of the workers along it,\u201ccaisson disease.\u201d This project began in 1869 and was opened in 1883 as Chester Arthur walked along it. Washington Roebling oversaw the creation of, for ten points, what bridge connecting Manhattan to a namesake New York borough?", "answer": "<b> Brooklyn Bridge</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The majority opinion in this case cites<em> Pugsley v. Sellmeyer</em> when noting that it \u201cdoes not relate to regulation of the length of skirts or the type of clothing.\u201d Abe Fortas delivered the majority opinion in this case, which argued that \u201cthe petitioners were quiet and passive.\u201d This case arose out of demonstrations in support of the Christmas Truce. This case\u2019s namesake test has been used to see if school policies violate constitutional rights. For ten points, name this 1969 case about a ban on the wearing of black armbands to protest the Vietnam War.", "answer": "<b> Tinker</b> v. Des Moines Page 1", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "This man was accused of having \u201cundertaken to be the hero of the night\u201d among a group described as a \u201cmotley rabble of saucy boys.\u201d This man, who is buried in the Old Granary Burying Ground, was once thought to have been a slave of William Brown. A protest against the Townshend Acts ended with the death of this man, followed by four other deaths; their killers were defended by John Adams. For ten points, name this black man who was the first to die in the Boston Massacre.", "answer": "Crispus<b> Attucks</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "The founder of Fatah, Yasser Arafat, administered his main organization from this territory, which is named for its position relative to the Jordan River. For ten points, name this territory that makes up the State of Palestine along with the Gaza Strip.", "answer": "<b> West Bank</b> (prompt on Palestine before mentioned)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "After serving as a Confederate soldier at the Battle of Shiloh, this man joined the Union Army at the behest of James Mulligan. When this man heard that an officer in his \u201cRear Guard\u201d handed over a girl to be eaten by cannibals, he attempted to place the blame on trader Tippu Tip; that incident occurred while he led an expedition to relieve Emin Pasha. In 1869, this man was sent to relieve a Scottish missionary who was searching for the source of the Nile. For ten points, name this explorer who legendarily asked\u201cDr. Livingstone, I presume?\u201d", "answer": "Henry Morton<b> Stanley</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "In one of this author\u2019s novels, Urania Cabral lives under the Trujillo dictatorship in the Dominican Republic. This author, who fictionalized his time at a military academy in<em> The Time of The Hero</em>, created the character of Pedro Camacho, who works for Radio Panamericano during the 1950s. For ten points, name this winner of the 2010 Nobel Prize in Literature, a Peruvian author who wrote<em> Aunt Julia and the</em> <em>Scriptwriter</em>.", "answer": "Mario<b> Vargas Llosa</b> (prompt on Vargas or Llosa alone) Page 2", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Misc Literature"}, {"question": "The art of these people prominently features falcon warriors in a non-Chilean Birdman cult that formed part of a \u201cCeremonial Complex.\u201d These people were succeeded by the Woodland culture, and they succeeded the Hopewell people. These people erected a series of cedar posts dubbed Woodhenge and constructed an earthen pyramid at Cahokia. For ten points, name this pre-Columbian Native American culture that inhabited land around a namesake river.", "answer": "<b> Mississippi</b>an culture", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "In the 1500s, this city\u2019s House of Trade handled a 20 percent tax on all precious metals passing into its country. Christopher Columbus is buried underneath a cathedral in this city, which is located on the Guadalquivir River. Legends claim that Heracles founded this inland city and a nearby port city as he passed through the Strait of Gibraltar. Twelve years after the fall of Cordoba, this city was captured by Ferdinand III of Castile in 1248. For ten points, name this largest city in Andalusia.", "answer": "<b> Seville</b> (accept<b> Sevilla</b>)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This country was the adopted home of Hugh Cholmondeley [chum-lee], the man who first coined the term \u201cwhite hunter\u201d for safari hunting westerners; he belonged to this country\u2019s scandalous white Happy Valley Set. A dispute over this country\u2019s north caused the Shifta War. Dedan Kimathi was killed in this country while leading a rebellion that led to the jailing of the Kapenguria Six. The Mau Mau Rebellion occurred in, for ten points, what country first led by Jomo Kenyatta?", "answer": "<b> Kenya</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "A cartoon satirizing this program shows a group of leaders dressed as Boy Scouts marching in front of a bus with the word \u201cRuin\u201d printed on it. Hjalmar Schacht was the president of an institution reorganized by this program. A $200 million loan was provided as part of this plan, which created the Reichsmark. Owen Young named a successor to this program that included a twenty percent reduction in certain debts. For ten points, name this 1924 plan intended to help Germany pay its World War I reparations.", "answer": "<b> Dawes</b> Plan", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "A school of composers named for this city was led by Palestrina. When a 14-year-old Mozart visited this city, he listened to two performances of Gregorio Allegri\u2019s<em> Miserere</em> [miz-eh-rare-ee] and transcribed the piece from memory. Ottorino Respighi\u2019s trilogy of tone poems about this city include depictions of its <em>Fountains</em>, including the Triton Fountain and the Trevi Fountain, and its<em> Pines</em>, such as the \u201cPines of the Appian Way.\u201d For ten points, name this Italian city.", "answer": "<b> Rome</b> (do not accept Vatican City)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "In this film, a bag of diamonds is given as a bribe to convince a man to redirect a train. Near the end of this film, a ring inscribed \u201cWhoever saves one life, saves the world\u201d is given to the title character. At age 3, Oliwia Dabrowska played a girl in a red coat in this film, whose director refused to take a salary for it. Itzhak Stern assists the protagonist of this film, in which Amon Goth oversees a concentration camp. For ten points, name this Steven Spielberg film about a factory owner who saves over 1,000 Jews during the Holocaust.", "answer": "<b> Schindler\u2019s List</b>", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Film"}, {}, {}, {}, {"question": "<b>Religious practices in this modern-day country include the Shaking Tent ritual and a regular re-burial of the corpses of those who had died peacefully, the Feast of the Dead. The</b> <b>Montagnais lived in this nation, where the (+)</b> <b>Northwest Company operated. The city of</b> <b>(*)</b> Stadacona was visited by the explorer Jacques Cartier in what is now, for ten points, what country where Samuel de Champlain founded Quebec City?", "answer": "<b> Canada</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>This thinker thought that the \u201csublime\u201d was the feeling of experiencing something that feels infinite when one rationally knows that it is not. This philosopher defined the title</b> <b>concept as \u201cman\u2019s (+)</b> <b>emergence from his self-imposed immaturity\u201d in an essay asking</b> <b>emergence from his self-imposed immaturity\u201d in an essay asking</b> <b>\u201cWhat Is Enlightenment?\u201d This thinker explored the moral law in his (*)</b> <b>\u201cWhat Is Enlightenment?\u201d This thinker explored the moral law in his (*)</b> <em>Metaphysics of</em> <em>Morals</em> and the earlier<em> Groundwork</em>. For ten points, name this German philosopher who formulated the categorical imperative and wrote the<em> Critique of Pure Reason</em>.", "answer": "Immanuel<b> Kant</b>", "metadata": "Philosophy - Philosophy"}, {}, {"question": "<b>A Czech artist from this movement created paintings like</b><em><b> The Bulgarian Tsar Simeon </b></em><b>and</b><em><b> The Battle of Grunwald</b></em><b> as part of his</b><em><b> Slav Epic</b></em><b>. Alphonse Mucha was an artist in this</b> <b>movement, in which an architect developed the \u201cbiomorphic whiplash\u201d (+)</b> <b>curvilinear</b> <b>style in his Hotel Tassel. Hector Guimard created the Abbesses Station in this style as part of his design of the Paris Metro. The Chicago (*) </b> World\u2019s Fair showcased lamps created in this style by Louis Comfort Tiffany. Art Deco essentially replaced, for ten points, what 19th century art style with a name meaning \u201cnew art?\u201d", "answer": "<b> Art Nouveau</b> Page 9", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Other Fine Arts - Architecture"}, {"question": "<b>This leader attempted to conquer Viborg from Sweden, but was stopped by the forces of Knut Posse. After the death of his first wife Maria of Tver, this man was encouraged by the</b> <b>Pope to marry the ex-Byzantine princess (+)</b> <b>Zoe Palaiologos. This man famously forced</b> <b>Akhmat to retreat during the Great Stand on the Ugra River, which ended Tatar rule in his lands. Later in his rule, he carried out a mass (*)</b> renovation of the walls of the Kremlin. For ten points, name this grand prince of Moscow, the first to gather the lands of Rus under one crown.", "answer": "<b> Ivan III</b> Vasilyevich (accept<b> Ivan the Great</b>; prompt on Ivan)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "<b>A million-acre grant owned by this man was sold in the Bingham Purchase. This man, who died in 1806 after swallowing a chicken bone, was sent with Gouvernor Morris on a mission to Elizabethtown to negotiate prisoner exchanges. This man became the (+) youngest major general in the Continental Army after his service at Yorktown. This man, who was succeeded in his highest post by Timothy Pickering, had earlier employed eighty yoke of (*) </b> oxen to transport artillery to Boston during a namesake expedition. For ten points, name this American general who later served as the first Secretary of War.", "answer": "Henry<b> Knox</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "<b>In this country, the Battle of Tofrek was fought by Gerald Graham against Osman</b> <b>Digna after the ambush and destruction of a William Hicks-led column in this country</b> <b>necessitated further intervention. A decade after Garnet (+) Wolseley\u2019s unsuccessful</b> <b>expedition against Mohammad Ahmad in this country, that revolt was finally crushed</b> <b>by (*)</b> Herbert Kitchener at the Battle of Omdurman. The Mahdist Revolt took place in, for ten points, what African country where Charles Gordon died defending Khartoum?", "answer": "<b> Sudan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}], "bonuses": []}